Beschrijving van de collection Cornelis Hendrik van Schooneveld
Universiteitsbibliotheek Leiden
- Professional correspondence (inv. nos. 14-25)., B.
  - Professional correspondence., 14.; Van Schooneveld's correspondence with colleagues, in alphabetical order by name of senders. The correspondence encompasses the period 1946-2003.; 37 boxes.
    - W.
      766. Wagner, L.A. - 767. Wasiolek, E. - 768. Wasson, R.G. - 769. Waszink, J.H. - 770. Waszink, P.M. - 771. Waugh, L.R. - 772. Weinbaum, L.L. - 773. Weintraub, W. - 774. Weir, R.H. - 775. Welcker, A. - 776. Wellek, R. - 777. Weniger, D. - 778. Wernham, C.J. - 779. Weydt, H. - 780. Whitworth, R.G.H. - 781. Wieck, F.D. - 782. Wiggins, H. - 783. Wilmes, K.-M. - 784. Wilson, J. - 785. Wilson, J. - 786. Wilson, E. - 787. Winer, M.M. - 788. Winkel, H.J. zum - 789. Winner, T.G. - 790. Winter, W. - 791. Witkam, H.J. - 792. Wittoch, Z. - 793. Wobst, S. - 794. Wolkonsky, C. - 795. Wolterbeek, J. - 796. Woltner, M. - 797. Woods, J. - 798. Woods, R.P. - 798bis. Worth, D.S. - 798ter. Wvasica, Josef. - 799. Wyka, K. - 800. Wynschenk, E.
    - Y.
      801. Yokoyama, O.
    - Z.
      802. Závodský, A. - 803. Zawadowski, L. - 804. Zeldin, B. - 805. Živkovič, D.; - 806. Żołkiewski, S. - 807. Zor, J. - 808. Zubin, D.A. - 809. Zvegincev, V.A. - 810. Zwanenburg, W. - 811. Zweers, A.F. - 812. Zwirner, E.
    - No author.
      813. (Biblioteka Główna). - 814. vacant.
  - Leiden University., 15.; Professional correspondence from Van Schooneveld, ordered by subject, from his time as professor at Leiden University (1952-1960).; 2 boxes.
    - Faculty of Arts.
      1. Appointment, 1952.
      2. Resignation, 1960.
      3. Faculty affairs.
      4. Professorship of Slavic literatures, 1957.
    - Leiden University, Board of governors.
      5. General correspondence.
      6. Slavisch Instituut.
      7. Secretary.
      8. Senate.
    - Ministeries.
      9. Ministerie van Onderwijs, Kunsten en Wetenschappen.
      10. Ministerie van Buitenlandse Zaken.
    - Students.
      11. Exams.
      12. Cards.
      13. Grants.
      14. Faculteit der Leidse Litteraire Studenten.
    - Various subjects.
      15. Leids Linguistisch Dispuut 'Nomen'.
      16. Fonds Croiset van der Kop.
      17. Nederlands Instituut voor Internationale Culturele Betrekkingen.
      18. Academisch Historisch Museum.
      19. Library of Congress.
      20. Congress of slavists, Moscow 1958.
  - Stanford University., 16.; Professional correspondence from Van Schooneveld, ordered by subject, from his time as professor at Stanford University (1960-1966).; 2 boxes.
    - Colleagues., Correspondence with colleagues, ordered alphabetically.
      1. Bowker, A.H.
      2. Brokmeyer, F.
      3. Brooks, H.
      4. Edeli.
      5. Kennedy, R.B.
      6. Kliachko, S.
      7. Kudrik, P.
      8. Lane, E.
      9. Lederer, I.J.
      10. Maichel, K.
      11. Miller, R.E. Jr.
      12. North, R.
      13. Politzer, R.
      14. Posin, J.A.
      15. Sears, R.R.
      16. Schuelke, G.L.
      17. Skarginsky, E.
      18. Sokol, A.E.
      19. Stahlberger, L.L.
      20. Stenbock-Fermor, E.
      21. Stenbock-Fermor, I.
      22. Sterling, J.E.W.
      23. Storey, R.
      24. Strothmann, F.W.
      25. Suppes, P.
      26. Vucinich, W.S.
    - Applications and vacancies.
      27. Correspondence with applicants, ordered alphabetically, A-C.
      28. Correspondence with applicants, ordered alphabetically, D-H.
      29. Correspondence with applicants, ordered alphabetically, I-L.
      30. Correspondence with applicants, ordered alphabetically, M-O.
      31. Correspondence with applicants, ordered alphabetically, P-R.
      32. Correspondence with applicants, ordered alphabetically, S-U.
      33. Correspondence with applicants, ordered alphabetically, V-Z.
      34. Slavic appointment: successor to C.H. van Schooneveld.
      35. Stanford University job description form.
      36. Stanford placement.
      37. Jobs 1963-1966.
      38. Positions available listed in 1965-1966.
    - Students.
      39. Graduate students 1962-1963.
      40. Former graduate students.
      41. Ph.D. candidates.
    - Various subjects.
      42. Travel Europe 1964.
      43. Travel recommendations.
      44. Relations with advisors to foreign students.
      45. NDEA 1966-1967.
      46. Foreign visitors office.
      47. Polish studies.
      48. Requests for miscellaneous info.
  - Indiana University., 17.; Professional correspondence from Van Schooneveld, ordered by subject, from his time as a professor at Indiana University (1966-1986).; 2 boxes.
    - Department of Slavic Languages.
      1. Appointment, 1965.
      2. Department of Slavic languages and literatures: various files.
      3. Publications.
      4. Secretary.
      5. Financial matters.
      6. Replacement.
    - Sabbatical applications and congresses.
      7. Sabbatical application 1979.
      8. Indiana - Strassbourg exchange 1980.
      9. Kiev congress 1983.
      10. Mucia grant 1983-1984, 1984-1985.
      11. IREX 1984.
      12. Prague 1985.
      13. Moscow 1986.
    - Research proposals.
      14. National Science Foundation 1971.
      15. Guggenheim Application 1979.
      16. Mellon Fellowship.
    - Various subjects.
      17. Indiana University 1960.
      18. St Andrews linguistic department.
      19. Texas Instruments.
      20. General Motors.
      21. 1983 recommendations.
      22. Launer, Michael K.
  - Correspondence with institutions in Eastern Europe., 18.; Van Schooneveld's professional correspondence with institutions in Slavic and East European countries.; 1 box.; This correspondence, mostly from the Leiden period. Deals particularly with such matters as cultural exchanges and book exchange.
    - Slavistic bibliography.
      1. Outline.
      2. Correspondence with institutions in the non-Slavic countries.
    - Correspondence with institutions in Slavic countries.
      3. Soviet-Union.
      4. Yugoslavia.
      5. Czechoslowakia.
      6. Poland.
      7. Bulgaria.
      8. Romania.
  - Letters of recommendation., 19.; Letters of recommendation, written by Van Schooneveld, ordered by year (up to 1980).; 2 boxes.
    1. Recommendations prior to 1960.
    2. Recommendations 1964-1966.
    3. Recommendations 1967.
    4. Recommendations 1968.
    5. Recommendations 1969-1970.
    6. Recommendations 1971.
    7. Recommendations 1973.
    8. Recommendations 1974.
    9. Recommendations 1975.
    10. Recommendations 1976.
    11. Recommendations 1977.
    12. Recommendations 1978.
    13. Recommendations 1979.
    14. Recommendations 1980.
  - Conferences., 20.; Correspondence concerning and items pertaining to scholarly congresses in the area of Slavistic and general linguistics in which Van Schooneveld participated.; 1 box.
    1. Trips, bills, reservations 1960-1962.
    2. 9th International Congress of Linguists, Cambridge, Mass., 1962.
    3. 5th International Congress of Slavists, Sofia, 1963.
    4. 10th International Congress of Linguists, Bucarest, 1967.
    5. 11th International Congress of Linguists, Bologna, 1972.
    6. 7th International Congress of Slavists, Warsaw, 1972.
    7. 8th International Congress of Slavists, Zagreb, 1978.
    8. Jean Baudouin de Courtenay conference, Warsaw 1979.
    9. Jakobson's 100th Birthday conference.
  - International Journal of Slavic Linguistics and Poetics., 21.; Correspondence concerning International Journal of Slavic Linguistics and Poetics [IJSLP].; 2 boxes.; Mouton published this journal, of which Van Schooneveld was an editor from its inception, from 1959 to 1973. Thereafter it was taken over by The Peter de Ridder Press and Slavica (Columbus, Ohio; later: Bloomington, Indiana). The files, ordered by year, contain primarily correspondence among the editors mutually.
    - Editorial correspondence ordered by volume.
      1. IJSLP vol. I and II (1959).
      2. IJSLP vol. III (1960).
      3. IJSLP vol. IV (1961).
      4. IJSLP vol. V (1962).
      5. IJSLP vol. VI (1963).
      5bis. IJSLP (January 1965).
    - Editorial correspondence ordered by year.
      6. 1966.
      7. 1967.
      8. 1968-1969.
      9. 1970-1976.
      10. 1971-1976.
      11. 1977.
      12. 1979.
      13. 1980-1984.
      13bis. (1987).
    - Various subjects.
      14. Slavic Bibliography.
      15. Secretary Annemarie Plate (Oegstgeest).
      16. Correspondence on 'review copies'.
  - Jakobson Festschrift 1956., 22.; Correspondence pertaining to the Festschrift that appeared on the occasion of Roman Jakobson's sixtieth birthday: Morris Halle, Horace G. Lunt, Hugh McLean, C.H. van Schooneveld (eds.), For Roman Jakobson: essays on the occasion of his sixtieth birthday, 11 october 1956 (The Hague: Mouton, 1956).; 1 folder.; The file contains mostly correspondence between Van Schooneveld and his co-editors.
    - Correspondence.
      1 Fischer-Jörgensen, E.
      2. Halle, M.
      3. Lunt, H.
      4. MacLean, H.
      5. Taranovski, K.
      6. Wils, J.
    - Various subjects.
      7. Proof.
      8. Copy.
  - Jakobson Festschrift 1967., 23.; Correspondence pertaining to the Festschrift that appeared on the occasion of Roman Jakobson's seventieth birthday: To honor Roman Jakobson: essays on the occasion of his seventieth birthday, 11 october 1966 (The Hague: Mouton, 1967; 3 vol.; Janua linguarum. Series maior; 31-33).; 2 boxes.; Here we find correspondence between Van Schooneveld and Mouton on the design of this volume, in which lists of invited contributors and Jakobson's personal preferences play a role. Also included are carbon copies, ordered by countries, of the letters inviting authors to participate in the volume. There is no further editorial correspondence.
    - General correspondence.
      1. General correspondence.
      2. Lists of invitations.
    - Invitations ordered by country.
      3. Austria.
      4. Belgium.
      5. Brazil.
      6. Bulgaria.
      7. Czechoslovakia.
      8. Denmark.
      9. England (United Kingdom).
      10. Finland.
      11. France.
      12. Germany.
      12bis. Hungary.
      13. Iceland.
      14. India.
      15. Israel.
      16. Italy.
      17. Japan.
      18. The Netherlands.
      19. Norway.
      20. Poland.
      21. Romania.
      22. Spain.
      23. Sweden.
      23bis. Yugoslavia.
      24. Switzerland.
      25. USA A-D.
      26. USA E-M.
      27. USA N-Z.
      28. USSR.
  - Jakobson Festschrift 1977., 24.; Correspondence pertaining to the Festschrift that appeared on the occasion of Roman Jakobson's eightieth birthday: Daniel Armstrong, C.H. van Schooneveld (eds.), Roman Jakobson: echoes of his scholarship (Lisse: The Peter de Ridder Press, 1977).; 8 boxes.; In contrast to the 1957 and 1967 Festschrifts (see inv. nos. 22 and 23) this file contains a nearly complete editorial correspondence: correspondence with authors, some of whom decline to participate in the Festschrift, along with the manuscripts (sometimes in multiple versions).
    - Editorial correspondence.
      - Correspondence of the editors with The Peter de Ridder Press, 1973-1977., 1.
      - Correspondence with authors, in alphabetical order by name., 2-80.
        2. Austerlitz, R.
        3. Avanesov, R.I.
        4. Baecklund-Ehler, A.
        5. Barthes, R.
        6. Bellugi, U.
        7. Birnbaum, H.
        8. Bolinger, D.
        9. Borgström, C.H.
        10. Bright, W.
        11. Bronowski, J.
        12. Bruner, J.
        13. Coseriu, E.
        14. Chomsky, N.
        15. Ďurović, L.
        16. Ebeling, C.L.
        17. Eco, U.
        18. Firbas, J.
        19. Fishman, J.A.
        20. Fox, J.J.
        21. Gamkrelidze, T.V.
        22. Garvin, P.L.
        23. Gove, A.F.
        24. Halle, M.
        25. Haugen, E.
        26. Holenstein, E.
        27. Hymes, D.H.
        28. Ivanov, V.V.
        29. Ivić, P.
        30. Jacob, F.
        31. Jones, L.G.
        32. Kasatkin, L.L.
        33. Kiparsky, P.
        34. Kristeva, J.
        35. Kuno, S.
        36. Labov, W.
        37. Lacan, J.
        38. Lévi-Strauss, C.
        39. Lichačev, D.S.
        40. Lightner, T.M.
        41. Linhartova, V.
        42. Luria, A.R.
        43. Maranda, E.K.
        44. Mares, F.V.
        45. Matejka, L.
        46. Mayenowa, M.
        47. Mel'uk, I.A.
        48. Miller, J.-A.
        49. Muljačić, Z.
        50. McCawley, J.
        51. Padučeva, E.V.
        52. Picchio, R.
        53. Pitkin, H.
        54. Pomorska, K.
        55. Pribam, K.H.
        56. Rensky, M.
        57. Robins, R.H.
        58. Ross, J.
        59. Rozencvejg, V.
        60. Rūke-Draviņa, V.
        61. Ruwet, N.
        62. Schapiro, M.
        63. Schenker, A.M.
        64. Schooneveld, C.H. van.
        65. Sebeok, T.A.
        66. Segal, D.M.
        67. Ševoroškin, V.
        68. Šaumjan, S.K.
        69. Silverstein, M.
        70. Sovrè, D.
        71. Stankiewicz, E.
        72. Svejkovský, F.
        73. Taranovsky, K.
        74. Todorov, T.
        75. Uhlenbeck, E.M.
        76. Watkins, C.
        77. Waugh, L.R.
        78. Winner, T.G.
        79. Worth, D.S.
        80. Zaimov, J.
      - Copy and proofs.
        81. Copy.
        82. Proofs.
  - Miscellaneous., 25.; Correspondence with various institutions.; 2 boxes.
    - Correspondence from the years at Leiden University (1952-1959).
      1. Publishers.
      2. Z.W.O.
      3. Dispuut 'Slovo'.
      4. Students.
      5. Ministerie van Onderwijs.
      6. Nederland-Amerika Instituut.
      7. Universiteitsbibliotheek Leiden.
      8. Ministerie van Zaken Overzee.
      8bis. Cour Permanente d'Arbitrage.
    - Correspondence from the years at Stanford University (1960-1965).
      9. Uitnodiging 1959.
      10. Secretarary Mary Patzer.
      11. E. Stenbock-Fermor.
      12 Danica M. Vanek.
      13. University Timetable for Ph.D. Candidates.
      14. Army Language School, Monterey.
      15. Booz, Allen & Hamilton.
    - Correspondence from the years at Indiana University (1965-1986).
      16. National Science Foundation Grant 1971.
      17. Research Project - US Govt.
      18. Council for International Exchange of Scholars 1978-1979, 1983-1984.
      19. Fulbright-Hays, 1978-1979.
      20. Irex Grant 1983.
      21. Irex Grant 1983-1984.
      22. Language.
      23. Booksellers.
      24. Indiana seminar.
      25. Societas Linguistica Europaea.
      25bis. Reidel Publishing.
- Scholarly notes and manuscripts (inv. nos. 26-30)., C.
  - Typescripts and manuscripts., 26.; manuscripts, typescripts, notebooks, index card files of C.H. van Schooneveld.; 18 boxes.
    - Manuscripts and typescripts from the Leiden years (1952-1959).
      1. Necrologie Nicolaas van Wijk.
      2. Klemensiewicz.
      3. Intonation.
      4. Russisch werkwoord.
      5. Postceding and preceding adjective in modern English.
      6. Old Russian tense system.
      7. Sentence intonation.
      8. Van Wijk Paterikon edition.
      9. Various papers.
    - Manuscripts and typescripts from the American years (1960-1986).
      10. Praguean structure and autopoiesis: deixis as individuation (diverse versies).
      11. A sign-theoretical model of semantic structure in language.
      12. Sulzberger Draft.
      13. English verbal morphology.
      14. Pronouns.
      15. Russian prepositions.
      16. Deixis et le modèle Saussurien.
      17. Retroprospect on the semantic structure of the Old Russian and Old Curch Slavic imperfect.
      18. Greek verbs.
      19. R.O. Jakobson.
      20. Contribution to the quest for meaning in language.
      21. Deixis grammar.
    - Manuscripts and typescripts from the French period (1986-2003).
      22. Phonologie (with H.W. Campbell).
      23. Latin.
      24. Greek.
      25. Research descriptions.
      26. Lecture handouts and notes.
      27. Premiers petits pas vers l'initiation à la langue russe.
      28. On the semantic structure of numerals in modern Russian.
      29. Dorothy van Schooneveld-Abel: CHvS unpublished and unfinished manuscripts (15 May 2007).
      30. Gender revisited.
      31. Theologie.
      32. A reformulation of the semantic features.
      33. Chomsky draft.
      34. Language - a model.
      35. Late Proto-Slavic sound change in formulaic notation.
      36. The passive transformation - a logico-semantic explanation.
      37. The article- what does it mean?.
      38. The postpositive article in Slavic: its definiteness and linguistic structure.
      39. Philosophietje aangaande het gereformeerde denken.
      40. The Russian accusative, mathematics and syntax.
      41. The phonological distinctive features as a reflection of the mathematical-semantic feature hierarchy.
      42. Agreement revisited: why agreement?
      43. Jakobson's one-verb analysis and the formation of secondary imperfectives in Russian: a few motifs.
      44. Autopoiesis.
      45. Draft of a paper for MLA conference in San Francisco.
      46. Jakobsonian phonology between iconicity and mathematical set theory.
      47. From Harris to Chomsky.
      48. N. van Wijk and R.O. Jakobson: a linguistic and personal retrospect.
      49. The structure of adjectival word formation in Russian.
      50. A theory of verbal lexical meaning.
      51. Introduction.
      52. Jakobson's one-stem analysis of the Russian verb and word formation.
      53. Reflections on ergative, case and the predictability of grammatical categories.
      54. A.T.G.
      55. Primitive terms and present-day linguistics.
      56. The grammatical system of the Latin verb and the place of the perfect within its semantic structure.
      57. Mathematical foundations of meaning in language.
      58. Peirce.
      59. Language as a mathematical mechanism.
      60. Conceptual features and set theory.
      61. Work description.
      62. In final Praguean-Jakobsonian structural semantic analysis conceptualization is mathematical.
      63. Saussure, our guide.
      64. Bare outline.
      65. February 29, 1992 proposal.
      66. On the predictability of linguistic theories and of their conclusions.
      67. Rhema.
      68. The semantic spider web of syntax.
      69. N. van Wijk en Roman Jakobson - een vergelijkende profilering binnen de Praagse school.
      70. Singulative identificational deixis, Russian syntax and a calculus of meaning.
      71. Untitled.
      72. Untitled.
      73. Primer.
      74. Praguean-Jakobsonian structural semantic analysis as an approach to linguistic cognition.
      75. Various linguistic notes.
      76. Latin grammar, Chapters I -X.
      77. Latin grammar: notes and prints.
      78. Greek grammar: notes.
      79. Three maps with sheets.
      80. Loose sheets and prints.
      80bis. Towards a heirarchy of phonological distinctive features.
  - Notebooks with notes., 27.; Exercise books and notebooks with notes on various linguistic and literary subjects.; 4 boxes.
    - Notes as a student of Nicolaas van Wijk at Leiden University (exercise books).
      1. Introduction to the Slavic languages (1).
      2. Introduction to the Slavic languages (2).
      3. Introduction to the Slavic languages (3).
      4. Introduction to the Slavic languages (4).
      5. Introduction to the Slavic languages (5).
      6. Introduction to the Slavic languages (6).
      7. Introduction to the Slavic languages (7).
      8. Introduction to the Slavic languages (8).
      9. Old Church Slavonic (1).
      10. Old Church Slavonic (2).
      11. Old Church Slavonic (3).
      12. Old Church Slavonic (4).
      13. Old Church Slavonic (5).
      14. Russian.
      15. Polish: conversation.
      16. Lithuanian: conversation (1).
      17. Lithuanian: conversation (2).
      18. 'Struikelblokken' (1).
      19. 'Struikelblokken' (2).
      20. 'Struikelblokken' (3).
      21. Russian literature (1).
      22. Russian literature (2).
      23. Russian literature (3).
      24. Russian literature (4).
      25. Russian literature (5).
      26. Russian literature (6).
      27. Russian literature (7).
      28. Russian literature (8).
      29. Russian literature (9).
      30. Russian literature (10).
      31. Russian literature (11).
      32. Russian songs.
      33. Greek.
      34. Persian (1).
      35. Persian (2).
      36. Persian (3).
      37. Persian (4).
      38. Persian (5).
      39. General linguistics (1).
      40. General linguistics (2).
      41. General linguistics (3).
      42. General linguistics (4).
      43. De Saussure.
    - Notes as a student of Roman Jakobson, Columbia University and Harvard University.
      44. Old Church Slavonic.
      45. Russian linguistics (1).
      46. Russian linguistics (2).
      47. Old Czech and Slovak.
      48. History of Czech and Slovak.
      49. Russian epic tradition.
      50. Structure of Russian.
      51. Retrospective phonology.
      52. Phonology.
      53. Harvard lectures (1952).
      54. Various notes (1).
      55. Various notes (2).
      56. Various notes (3).
      57. Various notes (4).
      58. Various notes (5).
      59. Various notes (6).
      60. Various notes (7).
    - Notes as a student of D. Čiževskij, Columbia University (bound notebooks).
      61. Old Russian literature.
      62. Russian literature of the18th century.
    - Notes as a student of John Lotz, Columbia University.
      63. Phonetics (1).
      64. Phonetics (2).
    - Various notes, Columbia University.
      65. Hungarian.
  - Index Card files., 1954-2003; 28.; Index card files containing notes on linguistics.; 10 boxes.
    1. 1954-1959.
    2. 1960-1965.
    3. 1966-1984.
    4. 1985-1991.
    5. 1991-2003.
    6. Varia.
  - Items pertaining to notes, manuscripts and publications., 29.; proofs and off prints of publications by C.H. van Schooneveld.; 3 folders.
    1. Proofs.
    2. Off prints.
  - Miscellaneous., 30.; Master copies of articles and various notes.; 6 boxes.
    - Master copies of articles.
      1. A semantic approach to the analysis of word formation in contemporary standard Russian.
      2. Semantic transmutations.
      3. Gogol' and the romantics.
      4. Article for Ružičič.
      5. Research outline.
      6. Semantic mechanism in word formation.
      7. Slavic word.
      8. Zur vergleichenden semantischen Struktur der Wortfolge in der russischen, deutschen, französischen und englischen Sprache.
      9. The cardinal semantic pattern of modern Russian.
      10. Allomorph versus morpheme in contemporary standard Russian and Serbocroatian.
      11. Nomen lecture - January 1971.
      12. LSA 1980 Summer meeting (Aug. 1-3, Albuquerque).
      13. Lecture Stanford April 6, 1979.
      14. On the opposition determinate-indeterminate in the contemporary standard Russian verb.
      15. Semantic project.
      16. Baudouin de Courtenay's methodological premises for the investigation of language.
      17. Contribution à l'étude comparative des systèmes des cas, des prepositions et des categories grammaticales du verbe en russe moderne.
      18. Disenchanted Americans.
      19. On pronominal structures in Russian.
      20. The place of the opposition active-passive in linguistic structure.
      21. Retort to Brechts' review in The Slavic Review.
      22. Journal.
      23. Uspenskij - Work.
      24. Stankiewicz Festschrift.
      25. Conceptual features and set theory.
      26. The place of the opposition active-passive in linguistic structure.
      27. Vicimus draconem: on the nature of meaning in language and how meaning works in Russian, and, presumably, in other languages.
      28. A theory of verbal lexical meaning.
      29. On the morpheme structure of the Slavic word and Greenberg's twenty-eight universals.
      30. By way of introduction: Roman Jakobson's tenets and their potential.
      31. On the semantic structure of numerals in modern Russian.